A Guide to the Papers of Anna Cora Ogden Mowatt Ritchie, 1842-1860
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Anna Cora Ogden Mowatt Ritchie, 1842-1860
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8010-a
This collection consists of 8 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on September 10, 1966.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains two manuscripts: "To Harry Munroe," and an untitled essay on Greek and Italian brigandage.
Letters discuss her health, the weather, her writing including "Fairy Fingers" and "Mimic Life," Elizabeth H. Appleton, Thomas Crawford, Catherine Hayes, Mary Morris Hamilton Schuyler and the Mount Vernon Ladies' Association, Ion Perdicaris, William Foushee Ritchie, Randolph Rogers, Frank Slayton, Julia G. O. Smyth, and Henry Alexander Wise.
Variant Forms of Name
Anna Cora Ogden Mowatt Ritchie; Anna Cora Ogden Ritchie; Anna Cora Ritchie; Anna Ritchie; Anna Cora Ogden Mowatt; Anna Cora Mowatt; Anna Mowatt; Anna Cora Ogden; Anna Ogden; Helen Berkeley; Helen Berkley
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - "To Henry Monroe" 1860 Dec 4, AMsS, 2 p.
    Poem
  - "Greek and Italian Brigandage is a subject of almost as much interest in England as in Italy and Greece.. ." n.d., AMs, 12 p.
    Essay
- Letters
  - Anna Cora [Ogden] Mowatt [Ritchie], New York, to James T[homas] Fields 1842 Sep 23, ALS, 2 p.
    Discusses in detail: her desire for his help in publishing "a moral tale for the young" under a pseudonym. Mentions: Edwin Percy Whipple, Boston, William Davis Ticknor, and New World.
  - A[nna]; C[ora Ogden] Mowatt [Ritchie], Greenfield Hill, CT, to Catharine O Sargent, Boston, MA 184[6] Jul 23, ALS, 3 p.
    Discusses in detail: Julia Gabriella Ogden and her fiance Joseph Kennedy Smyth. Mentions: Samuel Gouverneur Ogden, Julia Fairlie Ogden, Typee by Herman Melville, and Lizzy.
  - [Anna Cora Ogden] Mowatt [Ritchie], Boston, MA, to Mr. Campbell 1852 May 31, AL, 1 p.
    Discusses briefly Mr. Campbell's having most of her published works.
  - Anna Cora [Ogden] Mowatt Ritchie, Richmond, VA, to Harper and Brothers, New York 1858 Feb, ALS, 2 p.
    Discusses Elizabeth Haven Appleton, on whose behalf she is submitting a manuscript. Mentions Cincinnati, OH, and Harper's New Monthly Magazine.
  - Anna Cora [Ogden] Mowatt Ritchie, Astoria, to S[amuel]; B[ulkley] Ruggles 1858 Aug 25, ALS, 3 p.
    Discusses in detail support for Mary Morris Hamilton Schuyler's organization for fund-raising for Mount Vernon Discusses briefly: Louise Ingersoll Greenough; her desire to see Ruggles; Mary Rutledge Fogg; Octavia Walton LeVert; the coincidence of the landing of the transatlantic telegraph cable and the first use of steam towage on a canal being on the same day. Mentions: Boston, Enquirer, Samuel Gouverneur Ogden, New York, Tennessee, Alabama, and Edward Everett.
- Engraving
  - Anna Cora Ogden Mowatt Ritchie, head and shoulders, right side, by J.C. Buttre, New York n.d., Engraving signed